<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE lesson SYSTEM "lesson.dtd">
<lesson>
<page graphic="example0">How did our towns and cities get their names? Many places in Great Britain were named by groups of people who founded or invaded them in the past, such as Romans, Anglo Saxons, Vikings and Normans. It is often possible to work out which group was responsible for a certain place name by examining the name's linguistic features - the elements that make up the word.</page>
<page graphic="romanintro">The Romans invaded Britain approximately 2000 years ago and founded cities that are still standing today. Many of their names end in -chester, -cester or -caster, such as Winchester, Leicester and Doncaster. These word endings, or 'suffixes', come from the word 'castra', which meant 'Roman Fort'.</page>
<page graphic="asintro">In 449 AD Anglo Saxon tribes from Northern Europe began to invade England. They brought with them their Germanic language, now referred to as Old English. They often named places according to geographical features. The prefix Combe-, for example, referred to a clearing between woodland areas and can be seen in several place names today. Wood- was sometimes included in the names of towns that were near a forest. Religion played a part in Anglo Saxon place names too. The suffix -stowe, for example, meant 'Holy Place'.</page>
<page graphic="vikingintro">The Vikings from Scandinavia began to attack Britain at the beginning of the 800s and their Norse language had a great influence on Old English. Many towns and cities today still show evidence of this in their names. The majority of these places are in the Yorkshire area, which was under Danish Viking rule for some time. The -by suffix found in Selby originally meant 'farmstead'. Other common Viking suffixes include -thorpe, as in Scunthorpe, and -ness as in Skegness, which refers to the town's seaside location.</page>
<page graphic="normanintro">In 1066 King Harold of England was defeated in the Battle of Hastings by the Norman French ruler, William, who became England's next king. Elements of Norman French are still evident in place names today, such as the 'le' in Dalton-le-Dale, which simply means 'of the'.</page>
<page graphic="normanroman">Of course, some towns and cities were invaded and renamed several times by different armies and show a mixture of influences in their names. Can you guess which two groups were responsible for naming the town of Chester-le-Street?</page>
<page graphic="example3">In this game you have to work out who invaded a number of towns and cities and drag the correct soldiers to that place on the map. Click the button to start!</page>
</lesson>