<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<witchquestions>
	<question quest="Why was it heresy not to believe in the existence of witches?">
		<goodanswer>The belief that there are such things as witches is so essential a part of Catholic faith.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>That would mean Pope John XXII was lying.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>It meant you no longer believed in the Church of Christ.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>That meant you were a witch.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>From previously rigorously denying the existence of witches, the Christian church officially outlawed witchcraft in 1320 when Pope John XXII formalised the persecution of witchcraft by authorising the Inquisition to prosecute sorcery. It was now heresy not to believe in the existence of witches.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: Passages in the bible such as "Thou shalt not suffer a witch to live" meant they did exist and to obstinately maintain the opposite opinion indicated you had given up the bible.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="Why was Maleficia and Diabolism punishable by death?">
		<goodanswer>It enabled the accused to inflict harm and death on others through abnormal powers given to them through a pact with the devil.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>It caused insanity.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>It was malicious and diabolical.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>Christians believed they would not be forgiven by God if Maleficia and Diabolism were not put to death.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>Throughout the middle ages, people accused of harmful magic (called 'maleficia') or of dealing with demons ('diabolism') were subject to imprisonment, torture and execution.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: it was believed that by selling the soul to the devil, people could create magic potions and recite incantations to HARM others. It also enabled the accused to cause harm through other abnormal powers such as speaking to their pet cat or bird which became their familiar and were able to do the witch's bidding; or the witch could get 'shape-change' a feat only the devil and his cohorts could achieve to enable them gain access to, and harm those who had displeased them.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="What was the main reason for this?">
		<goodanswer>King Charles VIII issued an edict against fortunetellers, enchanters, necromancers and others engaging in any sort of witchcraft.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>Prior to 1400, there were only white witches; black witches did not exist.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>The Black Death was the work of black magic.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>Queen Elizabeth I issued a statute against witchcraft and it became a secular crime.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>Before 1400, belief in the supernatural and spell casting had been part of everyday life, and witchcraft was seen as just superstitious beliefs of peasants, but towards the end of the 15th century, capital punishment became the common fate for those accused of witchcraft.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: Following the Papal Bull issued in 1488, calling upon European nations to rescue the church because it was "imperiled by the arts of Satan", King Charles VIII of France issued a statute declaring witchcraft a crime punishable by death. In addition, throughout the 1400s, literature written by so-called learned theologians and academics, is being published PROVING the existence of witches, and of course, the first important book on the subject of witches, the Malleus Maleficarum, has appeared in Germany in 1486.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="What affect, if any do you think this might have on witches and witchcraft?">
		<goodanswer>It strengthened the persecution against witches.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>It improved the status of witches to one of royalty.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>It weakened the persecution against witches.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>It made it okay to be a witch because one was already reigning England.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>The English Reformation (1530-1560) happened for the same reason as that of the Reformation happening in the rest of Europe - to break free from the suffocating grip of Rome and the Papacy - but with a twist. This reformation was more about the English monarchy having supreme control, including ecclesiastical control, and began with Henry VIII severing his country from ecclesiastical unity and becoming Supreme Head of the English Church. However, keeping both doctrines of the Church (Protestant and Catholic) and the ecclesiastical hierarchy, made it easier for his second wife, Anne Boleyn, to be arraigned as a witch and cavorting with the Devil. </cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: If the Supreme Ruler did not wince at making an example of his wife, the Queen, by proclaiming her a witch thereby as good as admitting he had married a witch but been blinded by her powers of sorcery, then this must be a royal endorsement that witches, what ever size and shape, must be dealt with, without hesitation. Never mind the trumped-up charges and lustful desires of the King for another. This upheld the departure from the usual, more thorough prosecution procedures to accept and believe absurd witness statements, including those from four year-old children of the accused; and to proceed without a defence lawyer for the accused.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="What role do you think the Reformation played in bringing the witch hunts and trials to an end?">
		<goodanswer>It didn't.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>It empowered people to renounce the devil.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>It encouraged people to more charitable and tolerant, and less greedy and corrupt.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>It started the English Civil War so people were unable to practice witchcraft and therefore it died out.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>The Reformation, i.e., the Protestant reformation and the Catholic counter-reformation, instigated by Martin Luther in 1915 was about returning to a true Christian faith; and not being misled or diverted by the Catholic corruption that was going on, e.g., people being able to buy salvation instead of having to ask it of God.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: In fact, quite the opposite. The Reformation as good as sounded the death toll for suspects. In 1560, the beliefs of the religious elite came to be a potent political and social force, with clerics and other members of the elites re-interpreting many folk practices as devilish and heretical; and the 'authorities' predisposition to suspicions of clandestine conventions - the symbolism of the witches' sabbat - intensified their belief that devil worshipers were reversing Christian ceremony. Hence, witch persecutions underwent a renewed zeal.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="What do you think Father Cornelius Loos is referring to?">
		<goodanswer>Profits made from those unfortunate enough to be accused of witchcraft.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>A new scientific method of turning human blood into money.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>The discovery that human blood can produce rich minerals.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>A new spell for turning human blood into gold and silver.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>In 1592 Father Cornelius Loos wrote: 
“….and, by a new alchemy, gold and silver are coined from human blood.”
</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: During this phase of the witch persecutions, Each procedure of torture carried its fee; "services rendered" by the torturer and other court officials were paid for, usually with the victim's money. If the victim had no money her relatives were forced to pay for not just the actual torture but the torturer's meals, travel expenses, "entertainment", and horse-feed, and the victim's ropes that bound them and the wood that burned them. After the execution of a wealthy witch, officials usually treated themselves to a banquet at the expense of the victim's estate. The persecution of witchcraft enabled the Church to prolong the profitability of the Inquisition. By adding witchcraft to the crimes it victimised, a whole new group of people from whom to collect money became vulnerable, and it took every advantage of this opportunity.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="What was the difference in the way witches were treated and punished compared to the rest of Europe?">
		<goodanswer>In continental Europe, witches were usually burned as heretics. In England they were hanged as criminals.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>In England witches were considered rodents and left to rot in dungeons while in continental Europe they were seen as a threat to the Church and crucified.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>In England witches were branded with the Devil's mark and made to do community service for the rest of their lives. In continental Europe witches were torn limb from limb as martyrs.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>In continental Europe witches were hanged, drawn and quartered as traitors. In England witches were burned as Devil's advocates.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>Once witchcraft was officially declared against the law in England, witches and witchcraft were treated and punished differently to the way the rest of Europe treated and punished them.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: Burning was the usual punishment for anyone whose crime was perceived as being against the church - it was not enough to kill heretics - the only way to purge them of heresy was to destroy their whole body.  In England, however, they were hanged.  This was because witchcraft was tried in the civil courts and not the ecclesiastical ones, and if accused of harming someone by sorcery, it was a crime parallel to that of a murderer who would be hanged.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="What was the main underlying rationale for this?">
		<goodanswer>Without a man in the family, women were more likely to enter into a sexual relationship with the devil.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>It was believed that if you could cure or save someone then you could cause them to be sick or die.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>Women had the means to suckle the Devil's imps.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>Men needed a scapegoat for inexplicable urges that arose when searching for the devil's mark on a victim.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>Witches were generally accepted to be women; usually single and poor - widows or young women with no family to offer protection. Any woman who was a little different and who lived on the fringes of respectable, church-going society could find herself accused if the climate was right. This would include anyone who had a squint, regarded as the evil eye, or who suffered from fits, considered to be possession by the devil. The same applied to midwives and women with a knowledge of herbal medicine.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: The man was the bread-winner, therefore, no man no bread which would inevitably mean having to rely on other people’s charity to stay alive and in times of hardship, charity is not so easy to give or receive; the man was the protector, therefore no man no protection against un-Christian behaviour; no man no normal sexual relationship and, being more carnal than  a man, more easily lured into a relationship with the Devil and, any and all dealings with the Devil was the root of all evil. It was this that gave the woman the power to harm; the facility to suckle imps; and the ability to arouse inexplicable urges in men; and physical defects, however slight, were proof of consorting with the Devil. This is not to say men went unscathed, but more often than not, men were accused of, and tried for, supporting or cavorting with witches.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="Can you identify which attitude belongs to which social class and from what perspective they are being said?">
		<goodanswer>1. English lawyer (1618): scientific; 2. German theologian and priest (1522): religious; 3. English churchwarden (1563): witness</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>1. English midwife (1512): medical; 2. Swedish farmer (1490): farming; 
3. American professor (1690): cultural.
</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>1. German environmentalist (1700): environmental; 2. English judge (1650): legal; 3. English baker (1646): accuser.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>1. English scientist (1570): scientific; 2. God; 3. Devil.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>Below are three extracts depicting three different attitudes about witches, expressed by three people of varying social classes.\n
1.	The bodies of aged persons are impure, which, when they [become diseased with malice, they use their very breath and their sight, being apt for contagion, and by the Devil whetted for such purpose, to the vexation and destruction of others." 

2.	". . . sorcerers or witches are the Devil's whores who steal milk, raise storms, ride on goats or broomsticks, lame or maim people, torture babies in their cradles, change things into different shapes so that a human being seems to be a cow or an ox, and force people into love and immorallty . . .

3.	"There is one in our parish that useth herself suspiciously in the likelihood of a witch, taking upon herself not only to help Christian people of diseases strangely happened, but also horses and all other beasts. She taketh upon her to help by the way of charming, and in such ways that she will tell nobody her sayings. "
</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: 1. This “scientific opinion” appeared in, "A Parallele or Conference of the Civil Law, the Canon Law and the Common Law", 1618, written by the lawyer W. Fulbecke; 2. This “religious opinion” was part of a sermon preached by Martin Luther in 1522; 3. This was a witness's statement that appeared in a churchwarden's newsletter; and they are all men's opinions.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="What was the underlying logic to this?">
		<goodanswer>Only a bona fide witch would have the ability to unearth a fellow witch.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>Non witches were too Christian to recognise evil.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>A witch would be unable to deny a fellow witch's allegations.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>Only a bona fide witch would be able to withstand any harmful charms or spells that the accused witch would try and put on the accuser to prevent them from making a statement.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>One of the strongest proofs against the accused was the cross-accusation by another proven witch.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: Witches were cunning enough hide their sorcery from normal folk but if not able to hide it from another witch who would be able to detect with her witch powers. Also, there was a belief that all witches met and performed Devil worship and rituals together so it was obvious they would be able to identify and implicate whom the other witches were. For this service, a witch might expect to live a little longer.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="Which of the following was this new law NOT intended to instigate?">
		<goodanswer>A mass witch-hunt by the people to ‘protect' themselves and elevate the witch craze.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>Protection for the people and their families from the growing trade found in selling exhumed cadavers.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>Protection for the people and their families from witchcraft and evils of the devil.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>A true and just way in which to deal with those who harmed others by way of magic.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>King James VI of Scotland, later King James I of England, took the responsibility of eliminating evil and witchcraft from his realm very seriously. Below are excerpts taken from the law passed by him in 1604:
“If any person or persons shall….take any dead man or child out of his or her grave, or the skin bone or any other part of any dead person, to be employed or used in any manner of Witchcrafte, Sorcerie, Charm or Inchantment….or use practice or exercise any Witchcrafte, Inchantment or Sorcerie, whereby any person shall be killed, destroyed, wasted, consumed, pined or lamed in his or her body, or any part thereof...shall suffer the pains of deathe.”
</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: This law was not meant to stir up the hysterical fear it did, nor could King James ever have anticipated the vicious nature that the persecutions would take on or the false accusations brought to the courts borne of jealousy and greed. The law was, in fact, designed to protect the people from the true evil of witches, in which he himself genuinely believed. Due to the medical practice of using cadavers to gain better knowledge, the clause regarding the dead seemingly was added.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="What do you think the main purpose of this statement, uttered by the brother of an English Chief Justice in 1682?">
		<goodanswer>To warn the judge about not believing in witches.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>To show his sympathy for the convicted witch.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>To show his distaste for the pack baying for blood.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>To champion and promote the judge's skepticism of witches.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>"It is seldom that a poor old wretch is brought to trial . . . but there is, at the heels of her, a popular rage that could little less than demand her to be put to death; and if a judge is so clear and open as to declare himself against the impious vulgar opinion, that the devil himself has power to torment and kill innocent children, or that he is pleased to divert himself with the good people's cheese, butter, pigs and geese, . . . cry, this Judge hath no religion, for he doth not believe in witches."</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: The hint is in the last line; that the judge does not believe in witches and, therefore, has no religion is paramount to admitting being a witch himself - don't forget, in these times it is heresy to deny the existence of witches.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="Which of the following does NOT describe this society?">
		<goodanswer>Witches would often fall foul of ‘authority' for no reason.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>On numerous occasions, petty squabbles or grievances between neighbours were the main initiators of many of the witch trials.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>Witches often came to the attention of ‘authority' after having the finger pointed at them.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>Witchcraft was about power. It was a means by which the less powerful members of a community could increase their standing relative to their neighbours.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>A witch would often only fall foul of ‘authority' if she first fell foul of her neighbours, by not conforming to their view of society, or by having a reputation that would seem to make her a likely person to inflict misfortune.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: Witches may have fallen foul of authority on the odd occasion without the finger pointing but as archival material shows, the most common sequence of events was the accuser (often female) would recount their story to a male member of the family (usually father or older brother) who would then, pressed by his conscience and morality, take it higher either directly to a member of authority or to someone who had access to a member of authority.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="What does this suggest about the pressures of society?">
		<goodanswer>Dirty laundry had to be kept hidden at all costs.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>Members of a community were expected to be pure at all times.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>Communities should always have one witch to blame.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>Lying was better than humiliation.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>For a member of any community, attributing any number of problems to witchcraft and identifying the witch responsible - rather than having to accept that the problems were retribution from God for sinfulness - would have been a means of saving face and protecting one's reputation.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Reputation meant everything in the eyes of society. As long as you could present a front that radiated that of being a good neighbour, pious, a regular church-attender, conforming to the current values of society, not too rich, not too wealthy and of good, solid family structure, you were a model of society and no-one would look beyond the top layers of the façade; as long as no crisis befell you or your family for this would mean God was punishing you for a sin committed by you of your family, and of course, there was no perfectly natural or scientific reason for milk curdling or your child getting sick!</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="Which group of people would be most likely to assert this belief?">
		<goodanswer>Prosecutors</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>Heretics</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>Monarchy</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>Musicians</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>An ‘enemy of the people' could all too easily become an enemy of God.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: The whole prosecution system relied on this justification in order to convict a suspect. The reasoning behind this justification was that the next step to causing animals and people to behave strangely or become ill by bewitching, was to cause their death by bewitching, thereby becoming an enemy of God and in the service of the Devil.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="What might this indicate about the life style during the witch hunts and trials?">
		<goodanswer>It was sparse, unstable, hard and unforgiving.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>It was challenging and difficult, but sociable and entertaining.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>It was less about survival and more about reducing the population.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>Although it was a volatile and uncertain time people had to pull together and live harmoniously to survive.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>The social, economic and climactic pressures of the late sixteenth century and the first half of the seventeenth century: poor harvests, subsistence crises, civil wars and religious upheavals, price inflation; may have been a major cause of the resurgence of witch persecution.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: This kind of lifestyle is hardly a contributing factor to a ‘love thy neighbour' mentality. It was survival of the toughest, perhaps even the meanest; starvation, war, the consequences of war, the consequences of poor harvests, brings out the survivor in all of us; add an intolerance to non-conformity and tension, fear, anger, unhappiness and aggression inevitably found release in an activity that would reap benefits either by acquiring land or money.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="What are the parallels between the English Civil War and the witch hunt craze?">
		<goodanswer>Witches were nearly always non-conformist in some way or another and considered dangerous, and both politics and religion together fuelled the witch hunt craze.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>Witches allied themselves with the Devil and rose against the Monarchy and the Church.	</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>The witch hunt craze was a religious and political uprising against the Puritans.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>Both the war and the witch hunts evolved around social class.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>The English Civil War can be regarded as a religious and political uprising between the Puritans and the Monarchy allied with the Church. The Puritans were seen as dangerous and non-conformist to the monarchy and the church.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="Why do you think war would have had an affect on witch hunts and trials?">
		<goodanswer>War created conditions of distrust, suffering and intolerance.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>War unified people against the enemy.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>War accentuated people's perceived unconventional behavior and beliefs.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>War was God's retribution for man's corruptness.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>By 1649, England had experienced what can be termed as two short Civil Wars or one long one with two distinct peaks. Whichever way you look at it, it was turbulent times for England: Parliament against the Monarchy, religion against religion (Protestant vs Anglican vs Catholicism), and the rigid, sparse Puritan lifestyle as opposed to the perceived idolatry lifestyle of the Anglican in contrast to the perceived corruption of the Papacy. Such conflicts were surely bound to pit brother against brother, father against son, and so England inevitably entered a time of strife.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Although all of these factors would have had an affect on the witch hunts and trials, distrust, suffering and intolerance would have played a significant role in the need to find a scapegoat, and as corruptness and unconventional behaviour were the Devil's work and the Devil was the enemy of all God-faring people, then those people would unite to eliminate the enemy.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="How might these beliefs help to inflame the witch hunt craze?">
		<goodanswer>Morality, education, and enlightenment led to more witches being accused and convicted.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>The higher the morale of the people, the higher the flames of the fire that would burn the witches.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>Personal morality was the one thing that separated Christians from the witches.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>Education and enlightenment for the masses meant more people would know how to light the torches when hunting for witches.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>Matthew Hopkins was the most productive English witchfinder - it is estimated that he caused the executions of 200-400 people in the space of two years (1644-1646). Son of strict Puritan (radical Protestant group that developed in England following the Reformation) parents he held, or claimed to hold, the office of "Witch-finder General" as bestowed by the Puritan Parliament, and practiced his witch-finding in Suffolk, Essex, and East Anglia. Personal morality, and education and enlightenment for the masses were two of the top Puritan beliefs.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: The more people took responsibility for their personal morality, the more they would be encouraged to become educated and enlightened, especially on how to recognise one who had strayed from society's current values and religious beliefs; at the same time this would indoctrinate the masses in the destruction that could befall a community if one straying from God was allowed to survive. So, the more people who could be indoctrinated, the more witches would be exposed and eliminated. Remember, rather than admit to a moment of weakness, or seek a more logical or scientific reason for things going wrong, it had to be sorcery and the work of the Devil. Even the moment of weakness could be attributed to the witch who had bewitched them.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="Which of the following was a Matthew Hopkins favourite for proving guilt?">
		<goodanswer>A retractable knife.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>A water pistol.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>The Dunking Stool.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>Russian roulette.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>Instrumental to the torture and inevitable punishment of witches were the witch-finders or witch-hunters. A witch-hunter could be someone who meticulously searched villages for individual witches, or it could be someone who devoted much of their time to the persecution of witches. Matthew Hopkins was decidedly the most famous of witch-finders.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: Since witch spots did not bleed when pricked, Hopkins would stab at such marks with a retractable blade, thereby leaving the victim without a mark however hard he jabbed - clear proof of sorcery.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="Why do you think this was?">
		<goodanswer>Elderly women were seen talking to their pets.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>Hopkins did not like elderly women with pets.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>Elderly women were unable to fight back.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>Hopkins had an allergy to animals.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>Many of Hopkins' victims were elderly women with pets.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: Pets of single women, old and young, were often suspected, and accused, of being familiars or Devil's imps, or having special powers to communicate with the Devil. Therefore, if a woman was seen talking to her pet, she was obviously communicating with the Devil.</explanation>
	</question>
	<question quest="Which of the following methods of extracting confessions was not practiced in England and Scotland?">
		<goodanswer>The Rack - A slow, mechanical version of pulling the body in opposite directions.</goodanswer>
		<wronganswer1>Knotting - Reserved for women with thick or long hair. It involved tying a stick into a woman's hair and twisting it tighter and tighter. When the Inquisitor's arms got tired he would hand the task to friends while either holding the victim down or just watching.</wronganswer1>
		<wronganswer2>Boots - Also called bootikens or cashielaws, these "cunning" little devices consisted of wedges that were applied on the legs from ankles to knees. The torturer used a cousin to the sledgehammer to pound the wedges in closer together.</wronganswer2>
		<wronganswer3>The Strappado - The victim's hands would be tied behind their back, the free end of the rope thrown across a rafter; then the victim would be repeatedly hauled to the roof and dropped. If this did not work, weights would be attached to their feet as they were being dropped.</wronganswer3>
		<cluetext>"Torture" was theoretically illegal in England, but once the devil's mark - a mole or other blemish from which witches supposedly allowed the evil one to suck blood from their limbs - was found, the Malleus Maleficarum stated that "common justice demands that a witch should not be condemned to death unless she is convicted by her own confession". To that end, torture was considered an acceptable means of encouraging the "witch" to "voluntarily" confess.</cluetext>
		<explanation>Correct: Although the Rack was used as a form of torture in England and Scotland, it was not used on witches but it was very popular on the continent, and in particular, France.</explanation>
	</question>
</witchquestions>