<lesson>
<page>The tropical rainforest of the Amazon you have just explored with all its plants and animals is a type of ecosystem.
Energy from the sun flows into and through the ecosystem as it is converted to various forms of food. Ecosystems rely on the complex flow of energy between plants and animals in order to maintain stability.</page>

<page graphic="example1">The plants and animals of an ecosystem can be divided into simple categories, depending on whether they are producers of energy or food, such as plants; or consumers of energy or food such as animals. The simple flow of energy through an ecosystem from producers to consumers can be shown as a food chain.</page>

<page>Every ecosystem needs to find a balance between producers and consumers in order to maintain its stability. When the ecosystem has many different animals and plants or a large biodiversity all interacting together, it is vulnerable to instability. Changes to one species, by increasing or decreasing the numbers of individuals can cause knock on effects to many other species.</page>

<page graphic="example3">Let's take a look at a simplified food chain within the rainforest ecosystem.
The cannonball tree is a primary producer. It adsorbs the energy from the sun by the process of photosynthesis to produce carbohydrates in its leaves and fruits.</page>

<page graphic="example4">The squirrel monkey is a consumer or herbivore and eats the leaves and fruit of the cannonball tree.</page>

<page graphic="example5">The eagle is also a consumer, but is a carnivore and will eat squirrel monkeys among other things.</page>

<page>Let's imagine that our ecosystem only has these three species in it. It is now your job to try and balance the ecosystem by adding in different starting numbers of these species. Watch how your ecosystem responds over 50 years.At the end of the game look at biomass and also pyramid of numbers. In this case there is a small number at the bottom of the pyramid and more numbers above.</page>

</lesson>