<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE lesson SYSTEM "movie_desc_document.dtd">

<document>

<movieinfo movie="ground">Forest floor
The floor level of a rainforest is a dark and gloomy place. Only 1% of the sunlight falling on the forest makes it down to the floor, making it a hard place for plants to grow. Because of the enclosed nature of the forest, the temperature and humidity are both high and remain constant, helping the huge number of insects and fungi quickly break down the leaves that fall to the floor. Juvenile trees struggle to grow here, waiting for a gap in the canopy to give them enough light to grow tall.
</movieinfo>


<movieinfo movie="understorey">Lower Canopy/ Understorey
The zone between the struggling plants of the forest floor and the lushness of the canopy is called the understorey or lower canopy. It is generally a fairly clear zone, with a few small shrubs and young trees growing through it. It generally occupies a space between 6 metres and 17 metres from the forest floor. Vines and lianas help to link the branchless trunks of taller trees together at this layer, cutting out light to the plants below, but acting as the zone through which most animals move – like a highway through the trees.
</movieinfo>



<movieinfo movie="canopy">Canopy Layer
This layer is vital for making a rainforest what it is – it acts as a roof over the entire area, keeping the environment below it constant, warm, wet and perfect for the many plant and animal species there. At this layer the trees finally grow branches and spread out, having made it to the sunlight. They cram the layer full of leaves, competing with each other to grab as much sunlight as possible. They are joined by a huge community of epiphytes, vines, mosses and climbers, all trying to get a bit of light for themselves as well. The tree tops are tied together with vines, and their branches are covered in mosses, bromeliads, orchids and other epiphytes, making this layer of forest packed with vegetation. Thousands of species of insect, invertebrate, amphibians, reptiles, mammals and birds follow them up here as well; this is a busy place!
</movieinfo>



<movieinfo movie="emergent">Emergent Layer
This layer is where the real giants of the rainforest hang out. Occasional massive trees break free of the canopy layer and stand alone above the rest; they are sometimes over 220 feet (68metres) high. These trees tend to be from species adapted to have their seeds dispersed by the wind, and so may grow for hundreds of years before they can successfully reproduce. They are so massive that they create a ‘rainshadow’ around them, depriving the surrounding lower canopy of water. They are used by predators such as the harpy eagle as a convenient look-out post for hunting, and by other species as a safe haven away from canopy predators. When an emergent tree dies and falls over, it can clear a massive space in the canopy, allowing acres of new trees to shoot up trying to fill the gap.</movieinfo>



<movieinfo movie="rainforestgame">Layers Game 
Well, you have seen the film, now it’s time to prove what an expert you are when it comes to understanding the past. The game that follows asks you to match the animal to the layer it belongs to. Get all four pictures matched correctly, and you will win access to the rest of the Rainforest area and earn the right to call yourself an Explorer!
</movieinfo>