<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE lesson SYSTEM "movie_desc_document.dtd">

<document>

<movieinfo movie="precambrian">Precambrian: 800 million years ago (mya)
This is the longest Age of all, and covers the point from the formation of the Earth to the start of the Cambrian, 600 million years ago. That means the Precambrian lasted for 4 billion years! During this time, the Earth slowly condensed from a cloud of gasses into a large, hot and violent sphere. It gradually cooled down and the minerals and elements settled into the characteristic layers we see now. Seas were formed and an atmosphere developed. It used to be thought that there was no life at all on the planet during the Precambrian; we now know that the earliest algae and even some worm-like animals were busily evolving in the newly formed seas.
</movieinfo>


<movieinfo movie="cambrian">Cambrian: 540 million years ago (mya)
Very little is known about what conditions in the Cambrian were like, but some guesses can be made. Firstly it was likely to be quite warm as the atmosphere had more carbon dioxide - a ‘greenhouse’ gas - in it. There was no land or ice at the poles where glaciers could grow, and so tropical currents warmed by the sun at the Equator were able to circulate the globe and keep the seas warm. The levels of oxygen in the atmosphere rose steeply during the Cambrian as life began to flourish in the warm seas. The planet would never be the same again.
</movieinfo>



<movieinfo movie="devonianv1">Devonian: 360 million years ago (mya)
The planet continued to be warm – almost tropical – during the Devonian Age. Coral reefs fringed the land and fish flourished in shallow tropical lagoons. Amphibians hauled themselves out of the water to bask on the shores and began the long process of taking animal life out of the water and onto the land, following the example of the plants. Tectonic forces began to nudge the landmasses together to eventually form the giant ‘super-continent’ called Pangaea, changing the weather across the planet again.
</movieinfo>



<movieinfo movie="carboniferousv1">Carboniferous: 300 million years ago (mya)
This Age began with a continued tropical feel; huge horsetails and club-mosses flourished in hot forests with monsoon rainfall while giant insects chased tiny reptiles through the branches. Millions of years later these forests had formed rich seams of coal. But towards the end of the Age, things began to cool down across the planet as Pangaea formed. Ice caps formed at the Poles, and the warm tropical seas cooled by several degrees. In fact, the Carboniferous saw the planet change from a warm, humid paradise to a cool, temperate place much like it is today.
</movieinfo>



<movieinfo movie="jurassic">Jurassic: 170 million years ago (mya)
The Jurassic started with all of the major landmasses grouped together into a single massive continent. The centre of this giant landmass was hot and dry and probably very like deserts today. To the North and South of this desert, lush tropical rainforests flourished, gradually changing to temperate forests and then cold tundra as you journey further towards the ice-capped Poles. This variety of different habitats was one of the driving forces behind the great variety of life in the Jurassic world.
</movieinfo>



<movieinfo movie="present">Present Day
We are all familiar with the wonders of the world today through a variety of wildlife programs. We have travelled through rainforests and Arctic wastelands and can see just how incredibly rich and diverse life is on this planet. It’s up to us to keep it that way…
</movieinfo>



<movieinfo movie="evogame">Evolution Game
Well, you have seen the film, now it’s time to prove what an expert you are when it comes to understanding the past. The game that follows asks you to match the fossil to the Age it came from. Get all six pictures matched correctly, and you will win access to the rest of the History of Life area and earn the right to call yourself an amateur palaeontologist!
</movieinfo>