<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE lesson SYSTEM "lesson.dtd">
<lesson>
<page>The tropical rainforest of the Amazon you have just explored with all its plants and animals is a type of ecosystem.</page>
<page>'Ecosystem' is the name given to all the plants and animals that exist within an environment.  There are as many ecosystems as there are environments on Earth.  Ecosystems are often complicated and fragile.  In fact, a general rule is that as ecosystems become more complicated they also become more fragile and at greater risk from disturbance.  Examples of complex ecosystems that suffer greatly from disturbance are tropical rainforests and coral reefs; these are also the most species-rich environments on the planet.</page>
<page graphic="example2">Energy that is derived from the sun flows through the ecosystem from the simplest plants and animals to the more complicated.  These are called 'trophic levels' and can help us to visualise what is happening to energy as it flows through the ecosystem.  Another general rule is that, as energy flows up to a higher trophic level, the number of organisms and the biomass (or living material) declines.  This is because energy is used up by the organisms at each level, and explains why there are more plants than there are rabbits, and more rabbits than there are foxes.</page>
<page graphic="example3">The ecosystem game is in three parts. In part one you must build a pyramid using the coloured triangles, each of which represents different sorts of plants and animals.  But how should the triangles be arranged?  If not placed in the correct sequence the triangles will fade and disappear, leaving the pyramid unfinished.  Using the information above and your own knowledge of the natural world, complete the pyramid and move on to stage two.</page>
<page graphic="example4">In stage two, the triangles contain plants and animals that are found in each of five real environments: The Arctic, South America, Africa, UK rivers and UK lakes.  You must complete the pyramid again but this time using real plants and animals.</page>
<page graphic="example5">Stage three is based upon a web rather than a pyramid.  Animals often eat more than one species of plant and animal; there are usually more than two solutions to the problem of staying alive.  Now you must complete the food-web using the plants and animals from the environments of stage two.  But this time some of the animals and plants will become less abundant or disappear.  This is what happens in real life when environments are disturbed by natural or man-made disasters.  Can you construct and maintain a web of life for each environment?</page>

</lesson>